The best engineering comes from a deep
understanding of why. This is James
Cowling, formerly the most senior
engineer at Dropbox, and now CTO at
Convex, and we dived into all the
technical work of his career. It's not
about getting a system to work. It's
what do you do when it doesn't work?
Simple systems are way harder to design
than complex systems. He also had some
interesting takes on technical
leadership. Really, a team should be
oriented around what problem do they
solve? They should not care about the
system that survives. I've had many
friends whose promotions were rejected
because their work wasn't complex
enough. Yeah, it I mean, almost angers
me. I just like it so much. Is there any
career advice that majorly changed in
the last 5 years? Someone will argue
back, "No, what you can do is get really
good at using Claude." Well, guess what?
It's not very hard to use Claude.
Here's the full episode.
>> [music]
>> Well, first off, your PhD thesis was
huge. It was It's 156 pages. I didn't
know uh
like theses I thought papers, you know,
maybe 10 pages or something like that.
It's its own book. Um It's very similar
to Spanner, ultimately. And it was um
what's funny is I did that work. It came
out a little bit before Spanner, so I
got a citation in the Spanner paper. But
then Spanner came out, and then everyone
kind of
everyone forgot about my paper.
>> [laughter]
>> You know, about the research, like if
you could kind of describe the the
problem that Granola was solving, and
you know, how it solved it, those types
of things. So, can we talk about that?
Yeah, absolutely. So, I mean, my my
interest in my career has been um two
two parallel threads. Um one has been
just abstractions in general. The idea
about how to build simple models for
complex problems, and and I find that a
very, very difficult and very
intellectually was like um design
exercise. How to design APIs basically.
And the other has been large-scale
transactional systems.
Um big fan of of transactions. And
transaction, you know, is do a bunch of
things at once. And and again, I think
transactions are just one of the most
incredible abstractions we've invented
because it allows us to to to manage the
probably the most difficult problem in
computer science, which is which is
concurrency.
Um and so Granola is a um
you know, that was a long time ago in my
life now, but it was a it was a it was
an algorithm for how to do
um distributed transaction coordination.
Um and in particular, transactions that
I described at the time as one-shot
transactions. I'm not
actually sure if that was a standard
term at the time or whether I made it
up. But um a one-shot transaction
meaning you kind of send some code to
the server and say run this function all
these reads all these rights on two,
three, whatever nodes at once.
And how to make sure this commits
atomically across multiple shards in a
distributed system.
But yeah, that was my my PhD thesis and
my master's thesis was on a on a um
um on Byzantine fault tolerance. Uh so a
consensus protocol
uh in the presence of uh malicious
nodes. So how to how to achieve
agreement in state across multiple
parties when there's um malicious
entities. And
I guess the most well-known work I did
um
as part of grad school was work paper
called Viewstamped Replication
Revisited. And that was uh
that was a paper on um
redefining a protocol called Viewstamped
Replication, which was a predated Paxos
a little bit. Very similar algorithm.
Paxos, Raft,
VR, they're all basic Viewstamped
Virtual Synchrony, all basically the
same thing.
Um and that was a that was a paper I
wrote at the time, which ended up being
I guess influential to a to a
a few really great companies like Tiger
Beetle.
You mentioned transactions, and I saw in
the paper there's this idea of an
independent transaction. And I if I'm
you know, understanding correctly, a lot
of the efficiency in a in a distributed
system is lost by needing to get
consensus and to vote for consensus. And
it I saw that in your research, you
found out a way to avoid needing to vote
to reach consensus. And you know, how
did you do that? Yes. I mean,
a lot of people I think think about
performance maybe from the wrong angle
cuz I think of performance as a factor
of just of this raw horsepower. You
know, how fast are your disks? How fast
is your network, etc. And And no one has
particularly faster disks or memory than
anybody else. Um what really matters to
performance in a large-scale system is
eliminating points of coordination.
So, it's how to allow systems to
progress
without having
without having contention between
parties. You know, where like you're
basically reducing parallel throughput
to serial throughput across large
numbers of transactions. And so, in
Granola, we had this idea called a
independent transaction. Again, that was
the terminology at the time
where there were, you know, two entities
are basically processing pure functions.
So, they have independent state and they
will both come to the same conclusion as
a result. And all they need to do then
is serialize those transactions. So,
they have to decide if it was to happen
atomically across multiple nodes,
what timestamp should it get? And And
Granola, the paper was mostly about how
to exchange these timestamps very
efficiently. So, how to how to have
multiple parties each propose a
timestamp and then choose, you know, the
maximum of these basically so you could
safely serialize the transaction.
And there's a lot more complexity that
goes into this. But really the focus
there was about how to maximize
throughput in a large distributed system
without resulting in the alternative,
which is two-phase commit and two-phase
locking.
And two-phase commit uh with two-phase
locking is basically the standard
approach for when you want to have
multiple nodes agreeing on the same
thing, where they both agree to lock
their state, not process any other data,
and then and then and then commit uh the
transaction. Two-phase commit can be
quite um one, it's can be low
performance because you're blocking
basically the systems for the duration
of the transaction. And it can be high
risk, too, because you are taking a
dependency on another node. You
basically blocked waiting for another
node to return. And so, that was what
Granola was. Now, um
I've kind of you know, it's funny you
asked about Granola cuz I forgot about
it. You know, that's so far in my in my
history, I kind of forgot about that
work. And I even forgot the phrase
independent transactions, to be honest.
So, it's it's it's great to hear you
bring it up again. But I guess all this
stuff does feed into all the work you do
later on in interesting ways.
When I think about distributed systems,
I think about you're at a big company
and you got a bunch of machines. But
when you were at MIT building this
thing, how did you build and test it?
Did you
you know, were there spare machines that
the college had or was this in the
cloud? Yeah, it's it's this was a long
time ago now. I'm I'm showing my age.
This was pretty early in the days of
AWS. And so, we had a a rack of servers
in our office that we could use. And I
was fortunate enough to be at MIT where
we could afford a rack. Um and there was
also um a service called PlanetLab. And
PlanetLab was like a big communal set of
nodes that um you could academics could
use to run to run uh tests on. But
PlanetLab was a communal system, and so
it was continually having problems. I
mean, it's just a free-for-all. And so,
for the longest time, I would just sleep
next to my desk and
wake up when a Planet Lab was free cuz
you know, you need to run some
benchmarks. These days you just spin
something up on AWS, but then I would
yeah, I would sleep next to my desk and
I would wake up in the middle of the
night or random times and check Planet
Lab status and then kick off a
benchmarking job.
Now,
this was right at the cusp
at when I think in some respects Google
ruined systems research.
And I say that with affection and
respect to Google
um because before then
most of the research was coming out of
academia.
And a lot of distributed systems
research was done on smaller scales and
a lot of the um the value prop was the
ideas.
So like hey, I wrote a paper. Here's an
interesting new idea and yeah, it's all
in theory. And so the the value that
came out of it was the idea.
Around about this time you started
seeing papers out of Google, Amazon and
these various companies where it wasn't
necessarily a paper about an idea. It
was a paper about a system. Hey, I built
this giant system. It has a whole bunch
of features, some of which are
interesting, some of which are not and
by the way it powers Gmail or whatever.
And that that um kicked off a pretty
interesting transition because at that
point then
you know, um program committees
reviewing papers started to expect to
see realistic benchmarks.
That frankly grad students are not able
to at least at the time produce. I mean,
we I wasn't running Gmail on my system.
Um and I think it did in some respects
obscure
intellectual ideas, right? Because I'm
all for like papers about systems, but I
think there's also value in a paper
about an idea.
You know, it's not we built this big
thing and it works and up to you to
figure out what's interesting about it,
but instead here's a new thing. You
know, there's a paper you know, an old
paper just called leases,
right? Where someone invented the idea
of a time-based lock, and it's just a
paper called leases.
And though that was a cool era of
systems research. I think a lot of it
now has shifted towards uh industrial
research, which is you know, people are
building stuff
with, you know, for practical purposes,
whereas I think it's hard for academia
to compete on pragmatism. And you know,
academia is really a great place to do
impractical work.
When you look back on, you know, you
getting the PhD in academia, being
enabled to completely explore an idea
versus going into industry, but maybe
doing
you know, maybe you worked on Spanner at
Google or something like that. You know,
when you look back, which path do you
think would be better and why? I think
there's a bit of a misconception a lot
of folks have about PhD programs.
I think a lot of students are like
high-achieving students in college, and
they think that the PhD program is like
college plus plus. It's like, "Hey, I
like learning things, and so I'm going
to go do a PhD." But it's not. A PhD is
training to be a researcher.
And for most people, they shouldn't do
that. If someone wants to be a
professional software engineer,
they probably shouldn't spend their time
training to be a researcher.
But with a really important caveat.
I think there's a really um interesting
and challenging developmental experience
you go through in in a in the PhD
program at a top university at least,
which is you get to a certain point in
time when you have a problem that you're
facing that no one else in the world
knows the answer to.
You have a problem that you are the
world expert on, and you can't you know,
you can chat about it with folks, but
you can't ask your advisor cuz your
advisor doesn't know either, right? So
you're faced with these difficult
challenges that there's you can't read a
book, you can't you know, you can't ask
chat GPT, right? And so you're forced to
go through a quite difficult and frankly
emotionally challenging experience of
being unsure, being uncertain, and and
learning to think for yourself.
I think that is really valuable for all
engineers. I think that was really
really valuable in my career.
Um I do see a lot of folks early in
their career
um
think that all knowledge comes from
reading or you know, absorbing it from
someone else or that there's a right way
to do things. But I think being in a PhD
program
um
or being faced with really demanding
open questions does train your mind to
be comfortable with that discomfort. Um
I mean, look
I feel um
I feel a little bit lucky that I went
through a grad school without LLMs
existing.
Because I had to deal with this
uncertainty. I I there was there was no
there was no crutch to help me out,
which I think was very valuable. So, um
Ah, I mean, a lot of a lot of in you
know, if you want to if you want to be a
researcher, go go do a PhD.
If you want to build stuff, go build
stuff.
You know? And I and you know,
since leaving academia, I've done a lot
of work that I I guess one could call
innovative. Like it it advanced the
industry in certain ways and did novel
stuff, but our goal was never research.
Our goal was just to solve problems. And
I think that's the difference. I mean,
in academia, your goal is to advance
knowledge. Um in in industry, your goal
is to solve problems.
Um and
I gravitate more towards the solving
problems.
And I find that a more comfort-
comfortable environment within which to
work.
Going to your time in in industry, you
know, at Dropbox, you became the most
senior engineer at the company. And
looking through all the projects that
you did, I had a series of just
technical curiosities. I saw this idea
early in your career about multi-homing
and I wasn't familiar with that concept.
What What is multi-homing? What's the
problem it
Yeah, I mean multi-homing is the ability
to have data in two locations, two
homes. And multi-homing can be valuable
for a variety of reasons. Um one is
called, you know, primary secondary or,
you know, lazily replicated multi-homing
whereby all rights commit
authoritatively in one region and get
replicated to a secondary region. Um and
so this is normally used for, you know,
business continuity. You know, one thing
we did at Dropbox we made sure that if
the entire West Coast
blew up, you know, hopefully wouldn't
happen, Dropbox would keep running
because there would be enough the data
be replicated in other regions. But with
a window of vulnerability, with a window
of time where there may be some some
some data lost.
Um so that is, you know, that's kind of
primary secondary replication or
multi-homing. There's something else
called active active multi-homing where
there is truly an authoritative copy of
the data in multiple locations. So
basically when you, for example, write
to a system, you don't externalize that
right as having succeeded until it has
landed in all the regions.
Um and so, for example, in the the
storage system at Dropbox, the block
storage system, we truly had a a
multi-region replicated system where we
could take down an entire region, say
take down the a region in Ashburn,
Virginia where
everyone's data centers are and there'd
be zero downtime for the company and the
data was still safe in multiple regions.
I think multi-homing
is something a lot of engineers aspire
to work on cuz it's it seems like
the right thing to do.
But I think the reality is for most
companies it is not.
For most companies it's not because
there's very high cost there's very high
cost latency costs for this. Very high
um because the speed of light is just
not getting faster. The speed of light
is fixed.
And if you have to, you know,
synchronously write data across multiple
regions in the United States, you're
going to have, say, 60 milliseconds in
the commit path of your protocol, which
for most applications is not tenable. Uh
so, there is a lot of desire, um you
know,
a lot of engineering teams reach out for
kind of advice on how to adopt
active-active multi-homing for the
company. I would normally say, "Don't do
it." I would normally say,
"Frankly, if US East is down, if Amazon
is down that day,
that's okay. If Amazon's down
that day, your your company will be
down. That's a shame, right? But, by
avoiding that complexity, you're going
to be able to move much faster and build
a much better product. And so,
in my mind, systems is all about
trade-offs and making the right ones.
I would generally recommend most people
do not make the trade-off to have
partition tolerance or or or
multi-region availability.
Even though for a company like Dropbox,
yes, that does make sense. When you When
you When your When your job is storing
data and you have several exabytes of it
and and hundreds of millions of
customers, I think that's when it's when
it starts to make sense.
So, it's it's just another term for, I
guess, data replication and having it
available in other regions. Okay. I
imagine also, I mean, the cost of
storage is a concern. How many replicas
would you keep for something like, let's
just say I stored something in Dropbox.
It's my document. Is that
on on the order of one or two, or is
there multiple?
>> No, it's on the order of many, many. And
so, um
so, if you were to store a file in
Dropbox,
I modeled the storage to be, as we
advertise, at least 12 nines of
durability. Internally, the models look
around 24 nines of durability. And so,
that means the data is secure with
99.99999%
where there's 24 nines, right? Which
means at least according to the model,
you know, the universe will be extinct
before any data is lost. Right. And And
the way that is done is by a combination
of of what's called erasure coding. So,
erasure coding is how you take a
several blocks of data and combine them
together in it with an encoding scheme
and spread them around in in different
locations. At that scale, at Dropbox
scale, you're you're taking things into
consideration like putting data in
different racks, different rows of a
data center because they're on different
power feeds. You're taking into
consideration different eras of hard
drives and different manufacturers of
drives because they can have correlated
failure patterns. And then replication
across regions.
Um so, you know, you you could be
looking at
27 fragments, for example. That doesn't
mean you're storing 27 times the data.
It's it's kind of encoded in in many
regions. But, it's really the
replication schemes get really quite
sophisticated at that point. And we
actually had our own
custom encoding matrix we had developed.
It's called a Vandermonde matrix where
you kind of take a bunch of data and you
combine it together to produce outputs.
And we would plug in some variables like
how much do disks cost? How much does
network bandwidth cost?
Because there's a trade-off. You can
either store If you don't want to lose
your data, you can store more copies on
more disks.
Or you can store fewer copies. And
anytime a disk fails, you re-replicate
it really fast. And re-replicating
really fast costs
disk band costs network bandwidth. So,
these kind of variables go into this
equation. Uh it ends up being an
extremely complex field of endeavor, but
it's kind of abstracted away into a part
of the system that doesn't doesn't leak
into anywhere else.
So, with erasure encoding, my my
document in Dropbox is fragmented into a
bunch of different chunks of data and
loaded potentially from many different
machines. Yes, absolutely. It
I mean, the the first thought I have is
now there's uh I might be waiting there
and one of the 27 machines is slow and I
can't look at the whole doc. So, how do
you prevent against that?
>> It's actually faster than not
replicated. Because if you imagine I'll
I'll pick a
uh
a simplified example.
Imagine this is not the encoding scheme
Dropbox uses, but imagine to reconstruct
a file, you have to read six out of nine
fragments.
Right? So, if you read six out of nine
fragments, you can just ask all nine
and reconstruct and return the data as
soon as you've heard from the first six.
It's actually
faster and you can construct these
encoding matrices. So, if it is it's
actually faster to have a ratio coded
data than than not.
I see. Okay, so you can
like oversubscribe, over request and
then you complete on a portion of them
being received.
>> Yes. Now,
in in practice, it was a bit more
complex than that. We'd often have a
copy in a single disk to provide fast
access. We'd often try to make sure that
you could serve your data out of a
region close to your home region. So,
we'd make sure that your data was mostly
served with low latency, but if that
region had failed, you could reconstruct
it from the remaining regions. So,
there's a lot of um
a lot of people, you know, there's a lot
of talk about building your own
infrastructure and and you can save
money by moving off the cloud.
Um
almost definitely you can't. Unless you
unless you either you have very small
requirements or very fixed requirements
or very very very heavy investment. Cuz
if you want to compete with Amazon, if
you want to build a more efficient
storage system than Amazon, you have to
have a supply chain team that's working
with you know, Western Digital and
Seagate constantly and negotiating on
prices of disks and buying shipments at
certain time and and capacity teams and
and data center teams. Like there's a
lot of work that goes into like
optimizing this. Because ultimately, our
desire was to use the disks to 90 95% of
the disk size to to maximize storage
efficiency. To put it this way, I mean
that was you know, I guess it's a
ballpark figure a billion-dollar
project.
Right? And was you know, and it I think
at the time as far as I know was the
largest ever data migration in history,
I think at the time. And so extremely
large engineering project with very high
technical investment. So yes, if you
have that scale and you have the
engineering team to do it and you're
willing to keep innovating, if you're
willing to keep
um optimizing and investing effort in
it, then yes, you can do it.
Um but I think the real I mean the cloud
has been an incredible innovation,
right? Most people are not experts at
this, and most people should not be
experts at this. You know, most people
should focus on their applications.
When you say that most people shouldn't,
my immediate thought was but one of the
big projects you worked on at Dropbox
was my migrating away from S3. Yes, yes.
>> So,
um you know, why why did Dropbox migrate
away from S3?
Yeah, that was a desire of the company
for a long time. You know, from even
before I was there. So, I started at
Dropbox in 20
uh 2012. Um and I spoke to to Drew, the
Dropbox founder, I think in 2010 about
this project. And so I think there was a
desire to
um control the destiny of the company
from a strategic perspective. I mean, at
the time is before Dropbox kind of
reshaped itself as being more about
collaboration. You know, at the time it
was a file sync and share category. That
was that was the that was the that was
the market sector, you know? And so and
owning the file system was really
valuable to the company.
Ultimately, we saved a huge amount of
money. I mean, we we And this is before
the public company went public. We
really drove massive cost efficiencies
through the project. Um but it was hard,
you know, in a way that I think it'd be
very difficult to to emulate without a
huge investment.
And I do think that there is
um
there is a benefit to an organization
from having hard problems to solve.
Because if you have a a company with
extremely hard technical challenges, you
can
attract engineers who like working on
those hard technical problems. And when
they've solved those problems, they
cycle off and work on different parts of
the system. So, you know, after we all
worked we had a such a great team. It
was a very very small engineering team.
And after we kind of shipped the the
storage system reliably, we all went off
and you know, Jamie went and and
redesigned the sync protocol, the
desktop client, and I worked on the on
the file system and the distributed
databases. And so, yeah, there's there's
value to a business to have
um that level of technical investment,
but it is uh
you know, it's like it's like having a
baby and then you have to you've got to
raise the baby. You can't just build a
system like this and be that's it, we're
done.
You own it and you have to keep
investing in it.
Did um
did S3 do any counter negotiation before
you set out to leave them? Did they say
like, "Oh, you know, we'll cut you a
deal if you
>> [laughter]
>> I guess I'm allowed to talk about this
now. It was a long time ago.
Yeah, for the longest time they I don't
think they were they were particularly
aware that this was happening.
Um but you know, the the data center
folks talk. And uh certainly it was
noticed that Dropbox is buying up a lot
of data center space. So, yeah, we had
we had um obviously at uh at the scales
that we were at, I mean, we were
negotiating very good rates with Amazon.
You know, we weren't paying sticker
price, we were paying very very very
good discounted rates. Um but yeah, at a
certain point they weren't able to meet
our cost efficiency. Because it it's it
when we launched the system, it really
was
more efficient than S3.
And that's for a variety of reasons. One
was that we were using kind of new
experimental disks called shingled
magnetic recording. We were the first
ones, I think, to use these disks at
scale.
Um and two, we had a very tight
understanding of our workloads. So, we
were able to design the system
specifically optimized for our
workloads, whereas S3 has to design the
system for everybody. So, you know, it
it got to the point where, you know,
Amazon would not have been able to offer
us a more competitive deal because we
had a more efficient system.
Um
I wouldn't recommend another company do
this right now.
Uh but I think at the time it
certainly made sense for us as a
company.
Can you give an example of uh tight
understanding of your workload leading
to like something you could do that S3
couldn't?
>> Yeah, absolutely. So, for example, I
know
that um well, I'll try not to leak any
confidential data, right? But when you
when you upload a file to Dropbox, there
is a pattern of access, right? Um so,
typically people um access the file very
quickly shortly afterwards um because
you're sharing it with someone or maybe
Dropbox is processing that file to
generate an image preview. And then it
decays at a certain rate. And so, we
understand in general the average block
size, and we um understand also the
access pattern. So, we could do things
like at a certain point we had these two
um clusters. One was at One was um
designed for kind of temporary storage
that was kind of storage-inefficient
but access-efficient. So, it was very
cheap to read and write to, but it was
inefficient to store. And data would get
written to there first, and then in the
background it would get um moved in bulk
to this colder storage system.
And this colder storage system was far
more static.
And so, it was able to have kind of more
efficient algorithms and and and be
written to in bulk. And if it went down,
for writes that was no problems because
it wasn't in the live path. And so,
we're were to trade off, again, like
systems is all about trade-offs. So, we
were able to trade off the the live data
write path from the long-term read path.
Um that's one of many examples where
knowing the size of your data, where
it's accessed from, how frequently it
gets accessed, how um how long it takes
to delete that data, you can really tune
a system
um to your workload. If you know, stuff
like looking at
um
even things down to knowing how much
power to put in a rack. You know, you
have a rack of hardware, there's a power
distribution unit PDU at the top of that
rack. It has a circuit breaker which can
handle a certain number of amps.
We would have to figure out, you know,
how many amps are required for that rack
based on access patterns. And there were
times where we got it slightly wrong.
There was times where
we got to maybe a bad batch of hardware
and disks were failing too frequently.
And as a result, we were re-replicating
the data
more regularly and I was getting, you
know, messages from the data center team
saying, "Hey,
we were one of the racks really hot
right now." You know, so that's the
level of optimizations you can make when
you get to that scale.
Um but again, that's multi-exabyte
scale. You know,
million hard drive scale.
Yeah, when I was reading about this
migration, I saw somewhere in the
migration
you initially started with Go and then
the racks or something that you're
running on the hardware itself was
ooming too much or
requesting too much memory. And then you
migrated to Rust. So, initially, the
prototype was in Python, if you can
believe that.
And to be fair, Python is actually
pretty efficient for IO. I think people
give Python a a bad rap for IO-bound
workloads. It's pretty good at IO. Um
but obviously, um
not great for concurrency, not great for
memory management, and um very hard to
refactor.
And it was critical this system was
correct. And so, we migrated everything
to Go and we built most of the storage
system in Go. This is before Go was in
general availability. I think it was
before Go was GA. Um and we built the
system in Go. Go is a great language for
concurrency, a great language for
proxies. You know, it's a really well
designed for like servers that moved out
of one place to another place.
At a certain point though,
we would have, you know, let's just pick
a number. Let's say a million. Let's say
we have a million nodes in the system.
And every node has um
some amount of memory, some amount of
disk, some amount of sheet metal in the
chassis, right? And we would itemize all
these things. You'd have a pie chart of
of how much money is spent on all the
things. And it would still have stuff
like, yeah, sheet metal and screws and
stuff. And so, you're trying to optimize
the storage and a big problem for us was
the amount of memory um
these nodes were using. Not just the
memory that we're using, but the
unpredictability of it. Uh with, you
know, with Go having a runtime and and
you know, in a storage system, an out of
memory error is pretty bad.
Because if a node runs out of memory and
restarts, that looks like a disk
failure.
So, that looks a lot like a disk has
failed and has to be re-replicated. And
so, a batch of nodes OOMing
can lead to cascading failures
throughout the system.
Because maybe um I remember a time it
was a band. It might have been De La
Soul. I can't remember. There was a band
released an album on Dropbox.
So, it was a big spike in load
um to a to a
a few files. So, it was very, very high
um bandwidth and it caused the the
machines to OOM. So, the those machines
uh OOMed, those disks OOMed. Um and so,
as a result, no problems. The system
went to try to recover that data from a
whole bunch of other replicas, right?
Now, all of a sudden you've taken one
amount one fire hose worth of load
coming in and you've turned this into
seven fire hoses worth of load coming
cuz now you have to do a more expensive
reconstruction operation, right? So now
you've seven x the load. And these are
the kind of cyclical kind of behaviors
that can lead to something called
congestion collapse. Congestion collapse
is when
workload to a system crosses a threshold
where it all kind of collapses.
So
designing against congestion collapse is
really the hardest part or one of the
hardest parts of Magic Pocket, which is
the name of the storage system. Um so
ultimately we switched to Rust for the
storage nodes themselves. And this
again, this is before Rust was in GA, so
that was a bit of a risky move.
Uh but we rewrote um
the switch to Rust coincided with
getting rid of the file system entirely
on the disks and directly addressing the
the disk disk heads. So there was a
there's an instruction set, I think it's
called ZBC, zone based block control,
something like that. There's there's a
there's an instruction set for accessing
disks that we were using.
The disk manufacturers gave us the draft
specs of these new disks and we were
operating off the draft specs and
directly controlling the the disks. And
so all that product was tied up um
together um
into a product called Discotech. It was
the disk technology project. Um and
ultimately, if you look at that pie
chart one congestion collapse stopped
and reliability improved. But if you
looked at the pie chart of where all the
money was going, it really shifted to be
almost all disks. And what we wanted to
do is get that pie chart to be
almost all the money spent on disks and
as little money spent on RAM, on
compute, on network, on power, on sheet
metal, etc. The cascading failure you
mentioned, was there So that that
happened and then there was a
postmortem. I don't think we needed a
postmortem. Well, I think we we knew as
it was happening.
>> [laughter]
>> I think when I was getting paged in the
middle of the night on these things I
would you know, you'd be pretty pretty
evident. And so look, this is the again,
this is an argument in favor of the
cloud. All right. Imagine you've spent
hundreds of millions of dollars on a on
a storage system and it's out in
production and it's on physical
hardware.
You can't just go and put new memory
chips in every one of them. I mean, you
can, but you have to pay people to come
in and swap them out, you know. And so
that that's a tricky place. And so as a
And this is what This is what I love
about industry. You know, cuz in like
some of the more um
challenging moments on Magic Pocket were
stuff like in one week
just a weird coincidence two trucks
crashed that were delivering servers. So
there's two trucks showing up to deliver
racks and they both crashed. I don't
know, you know, the drivers were okay.
So we lost capacity for 2 weeks.
Uh so the So we lost capacity for for
more than 2 weeks for for for probably 6
weeks.
Um
What do you do?
What happens, you know, is is the
equivalent of your disk filling up on
your laptop except it's, you know, it's
it's a million disks.
And you can't tell the customers to go
away. You can't delete their files. So a
lot of a lot of tricky
um a lot of tricky capacity work. Um and
ultimately what that what that led to
was trying to build in
all these protections against the
unknowns. You know, making sure we had
the right amount of buffer planned out
for anything bad that could happen.
Making sure we we designed the system so
they couldn't be congestion collapse so
there wouldn't be memory spikes.
Um
and
you know, at one point there's a there's
a process called I think it's called
FMEA
which is like a threat modeling process
where you had a big spreadsheet and you
kind of write down every bad thing that
could possibly happen and then, you
know, all the how bad it would be if it
happened.
Existential risk.
Did someone die? You know, if there's a
fire in the data center. All these kind
of things get put into the spreadsheet.
And you kind of do a bit of a almost
pre-mortem kind of work to figure out
all the all the potential failure modes,
and then design around them. And that's
I love that work. I I I really um
I don't know. I do like the firefight. I
I like the
I don't I can't say I like getting paged
because
I've spent my whole life on call,
but I do like that rubber hits the road
stuff. I like that
wow, there's congestion collapse and and
there's no one that can help you. And so
you've [snorts] got to
think through this problem.
When I worked on infrastructure at
Instagram, we had this concept of DEFCON
knobs, which are basically these configs
that you could flip that would
gracefully degrade your system, where
you can still operate it, but you know,
maybe in the case of Dropbox, you store
less replicas. So you take on a
temporary increase of uh risk in losing
data because you need to. Uh did you
have something like that, and did you
flip it in that type of case? Never when
it came to durability. So, I mean, we
just had a just absolute zero
non-negotiable, like there was no room
for negotiation on on user durability.
And so um
we had those knobs for background
processes, for CPU and and memory, for
example. So, if there was like a spike
in load, you could turn off background
processes and and turn off um you know,
um the the test load, for example, on
the system. Eventually, we we built this
system called
trampoline.
And what trampoline did was um which
actually was a it it saved us a ton of
money, right? When if we ever got too
close to the threshold, we would just
start writing data to S3.
Cuz it's right there, right? So, it's um
you can run your capacity way closer to
the edge if you're willing under worst
case scenarios just to just to dump 30
petabytes on S3, and then move it back
when it's done. And now, it I that
didn't happen very often. We would do it
to test it. We would do that to make
sure the system worked.
But um yeah, being able to have a escape
hatch for worst case scenario was really
nice. As you said, S3 is kind of um it's
like elastic storage. Exactly.
When I looked at this project, it's such
a massive migration and my first thought
is how do you coordinate this whole
project without breaking the system as
it's running?
How Yeah, what are your thoughts on
doing such a large migration without
breaking things?
>> Yeah. Now, I mean in
in terms of the engineers that like
built the initial version of the system,
it was a handful.
Three, four, five, six engineers. It
wasn't a team of a thousand, you know.
It was a very, very small team. And so
um
how do you build such a large system
with a small number of people and then
how do you do a high-risk migration? Uh
one of these one one thing you do is you
keep things simple. You you try so so so
hard to
build very cleanly abstracted, simple
systems that their failure modes are
very understandable. Um and so they and
they and they decouple so they don't
have congestion, collapse, etc. So,
focusing on simplicity this it gets
tricky by the way with people doing
agentic development. They're not the
best at building simple systems. Like
simplicity is still the domain of human
beings for now. But um a big focus on
simplicity. The other was um
you know, this this very thick layer of
validation checks during this migration.
And and in fact um
we had uh
when we did the migration off of S3, we
had this um something called the dark
launch where we would, you know, be
moving data off of S3, but we were
keeping it in both locations. And we had
to demonstrate to the we had this kind
of contract with the Dropbox founders.
We'd have to kind of keep the system
running with no incidents.
Uh no downtime, no data loss, whatever,
for 6 months before we would delete any
of the data from S3. So, we have double
write it. And um
And there's one point in time, halfway
through this process, where there was a
a bug got through to production.
Um, and it didn't nothing bad happened
with the bug. But, it was a it was like
a
It was it was like a a bug
slipped through our multiple layers of,
you know, release process, etc. And um
So, I went to the VP and I said, "Hey,
you a bug made it through to production,
and we're going to reset the launch
clock."
And as a result, it's going to launch
later, and it's going to cost us
some amount of money. Let's say
double-digit millions, you know?
And they were like, "Great.
Thank you. That's good. I trust you."
And that was that that was a cool thing.
I mean, Dropbox had a lot of incredible
cultural values. But, like, that was
like, "Okay, cool. If you're
prioritizing user safety, that's the
right thing to do." And
no one was mad about that. It was almost
like they were
proud, almost. You know, it was it was
just like a it was like, "Yes, you're
you're operating uh in accordance to the
principles of this company." And, yeah.
Okay. So, it was it was double writing
both systems for a while, and then Some
subset of data, yeah. Uh, okay. And then
you switched over reads. Once we were
sure the system was durable, and we had
all these validators running in
production 24/7, uh there was just
migrating as fast as we could. I think
at some point we got up to 700
gigabits per second, 764 gigabits per
second of peering bandwidth between
Amazon servers and ours. Um
Certainly someone on the network team
over there noticed
that [laughter] there was that much data
moving out.
At one point I got a a slightly nasty
email from someone saying
>> [snorts]
>> it was super weird. I think the phrase
super weird It's like, "It's super weird
that you're doing so many reads and not
that many writes."
Mhm. And I didn't didn't respond to that
email. But to be fair, like Amazon was a
a great have been a were a great partner
for Dropbox. And Dropbox still uses AWS.
They always
um
there was no concern that they would do
the wrong thing by us as a company. I
mean, like well we we only had excellent
experience with AWS. Um but yeah, there
was a it was a moment for us, you know,
it was a
it probably strained the relationship
somewhat.
You mentioned simplicity and intuition
wise, it makes sense.
Do you have a concrete example though?
Yeah, I've got a concrete example for
you. And it it maybe it shows the
difference between academia and
industry.
Um so um
the storage system is a giant
distributed system with a files stored
in various locations. And so you need a
a mapping from from the file to where it
lives on these disks.
And so all we did was had a cluster of a
thousand MySQL nodes.
All right?
Big giant database, and it was indexed
by the block ID, and it said this block
is on these disks.
And that's a pretty
like simple, it's not sophisticated, you
know? And it And every time we'd hire
someone out of academia or maybe from
other companies, they'd say, "Oh, this
is not very sophisticated because like
you could use a Patricia trie, or you
could use a distributed hash table, and
that would map um a block to a set of um
of of locations." And I think
that's optimizing for the wrong thing.
Because the really nice thing about
dumping a list of files and their
locations in a giant database is it's
written in one location. If I want to
validate what happened, if I want to
check all the data that is where it's
meant to be, I just walk over the table
and check. And we did. We had services
constantly walking over in the table and
checking. Whereas if it it a distributed
hash table or some giant complex data
structure, it's very hard to to
validate. So, I mean, designing for
validation is very important. Designing
for understanding is very important.
It's not about getting a system to work.
It's what do you do when it doesn't
work, right? And so, having a very
simple boundary That's That's a It's a
very basic example, you know, there's
there's more There's more sophisticated
examples that take more time to explain.
But, like, something like that is
a lot of engineers will feel, you know,
a lot of engineers will want to do
interesting work. Will want to advance
in their career. They They want to be
seen as a as a intellectual problem
solver.
And so, the tendency can be to design
complex systems. And my argument is
always that, like,
simple systems are way harder to design
than complex systems.
Like, simplicity is so hard. And I think
to like maybe the untrained eye, a
simple system can seem like obvious. And
the the the best compliment you could
ever get about anything you design is
people say like, "Oh, isn't that the
Isn't that the obvious way of doing it?"
It's It's like same as convex, you know,
people say, "Oh, isn't that
What's that? That's just like the
obvious way of structuring." Like,
great. Because it wasn't obvious when we
did it. No one else was doing it, right?
Everyone thought we were idiots. If
after the fact, people think it's
obvious, then you then you really nailed
it. I think um
But, I think that's a um It requires a
an understanding that's that that
simplicity is is the hardest thing in
systems. And cuz simplicity is
is scalable. And I don't Yes, simplicity
is scalable in terms of numbers of
queries per second, right? But, what I
really mean about scalability is you can
take a simple system
and and have it run for 5 years, and
have people work on it for 5 years, and
have all sorts of features added to it,
and have requirements changed cuz the
company realized the product didn't work
the way it wanted to work, and it wants
to change things, and it still stands
the test of time.
Whereas a complex over-optimized system
will not. And that's the tough thing
about
distributed systems design, especially
um
LLM augmented distributed systems
design, is just because something works
doesn't mean it's maintainable over a
long period of time. Doesn't mean it's
understandable. Doesn't mean it's
cleanly up architected and abstracted.
That stuff's really very hard.
Absolutely. And I agree with you. I
think it's the long-term beneficial
thing to do.
One unusual thing though in the industry
that I I've seen is
the incentive system for engineers is
actually I mean, you mentioned the
desire for an engineer to want to be
seen that they can do something
difficult. There's that, but there's
also the incentive system of promotions.
And I've had many friends whose
promotions were rejected because their
work wasn't complex enough. And so that
kind of forces It's a forces complexity,
which is kind of unusual. I wanted to
know what you thought about that. Yeah,
it I mean, it almost
angers me. I just like it so much.
Partly why I started my own company, you
know.
Um
I think
the ideal for anyone is to be doing work
where the you're being appreciated for
solving the problem. Like, you know, and
this is
If we get philosophical, this is what it
was like going back to the farming days,
right? There was no incentive to make it
really complicated to milk a cow, cuz
the goal is to like milk the cow, and
then the back The reward is you got
milk, right? And I think at a It sounds
so silly, but at a startup, that's the
same thing. The startup the goal is to
build the system, have it work, have the
users like it, have it grow, and
everyone gets rewarded and celebrated
for solving the problem.
It gets hard to scale that. So, at large
companies
the end up with so many layers of
organization that people end up building
alternative incentive structures, right?
It's like I'm so far away from whatever
the hell we're trying to do over here
that my goal now is to get all green
check marks on my OKR plan.
But who cares about your OKR plan unless
it solves the problem? And so the you
know, the thing that really drives me um
really drives me insane is when people
try to chase
um
artificial goals.
Right? And I And I understand that if
you're in a company with um like this
that you may have no choice in the
matter. But what I want to tell people
there is a better way.
And it you know, and that that better
way may not be available to you. You may
not
have job opportunities near where you
are, for example. But if you do have the
ability to go work at a company where
like you are being appreciated for
problem solving,
that will make you so much better as an
engineer. Like And I see this when I
when I interview people, you know? Um
and I if if I, you know, do a um
I mean, everyone knows Google has
tremendous engineering and tremendous
engineers. Um a lot of
folks there though, I'm not
that interested in hiring
because
you know, if I'll do a deep dive with
them and they'll say they built a system
and I'll say, "Well, why did you build
it?" And they're like, "I don't know.
The VP told me to." And like, "Oh, how
is this system used?" And they're like,
"I don't
I don't really know. I think ads uses
it. I'm not sure." And this is a this is
a caricature, but I think it's very very
hard to do good engineering in that
environment. You can do competent
engineering, but the best engineering
comes from a deep understanding of why.
And this is something we just drill into
you know, the the team here at Cockroach
or you know, the team embodies so
strongly at Cockroach is like everything
exists for the why. Do like don't build
a a fancy load balancer unless it's not
needed. Turns out we do need a fancy
load balancer, we're building it right
now. But but you know,
you should always start with why are we
doing this? What's the point?
And
I feel for people stuck in environments
that are not like this. But you know
what? Like I don't know.
Try to fight the system a little bit. I
think I do see a lot of maybe nihilism,
a lot of defeatedness sometimes amongst
junior engineers. A lot of this um
cynicism.
Like you know, what does it matter? Like
who cares? It's just a big organization
and nothing matters and but I think it
does matter. Like
I've just if I think of like the
happiest times in my life, it's been
like just
dedicating myself to a cause and
and
and trying really hard and and trying to
do the right thing and and I felt good
when I went home and and not trying to
get promoted, just trying to do the
right thing and then and then
assume me I'm going to get promoted and
if not go somewhere else. Um I know it
does sound quaint when I'm saying this,
but I think it's possible to do this and
especially possible if you surround
yourself with people like this.
And if someone is in a big company and
they're feeling frustrated by politics,
look around and see if there's a team of
folks who just seem to
want to do the right thing. Just seem to
want to do good stuff. I don't think
that's selling out. I think that's being
true to yourself. Like just
that's what real engineering is.
Not trying to make a complicated fancy
thing to get promoted. Just build the
coolest thing that's solves the problem.
This really reminds me of something you
had written and I thought it was really
good writing. And in the writing there
was this idea of system bias.
And
>> Yes. you you have this
uh quote your your writing. It says, you
know, here's some examples. It says, the
team is spending 6 months to improve
performance by 10% when it was
completely fine to begin with or you
know, the team is trying desperately to
force their tooling on clients who don't
need it or you know, the team is riding
their outdated system to the grave like
the captain going down on the Titanic.
I I've I've definitely seen examples of
all those types of things in industry.
Um
And so
yeah, it I I think it was it was in the
the
It was in the context of your writing
about
um what you should orient your your team
around, not systems, but actually
missions. And maybe that's a way to
fight system bias. Yeah, I mean, one of
one of my jobs at Dropbox um
wasn't the most fun job, but it might
have been one of the most impactful
jobs. It was shutting down projects, you
know, looking around and being like,
"Huh, that thing over there that
has had 60 people working on it for 2
years doesn't seem to make a lot of
sense to me." And then I you know, it
wasn't like a um
a hostile thing, but I'd go and chat
with the team and I'd say, "Hey,
what are you all doing? Do you believe
in what you're doing? Does this make
sense?" And the team in private would
say, "Oh, I don't really know.
But inertia is so strong, you know? This
whole desire to not get in trouble, you
know, to just keep doing what you were
previously doing is so strong. And it
And talented people can end up doing
things that don't make a lot of sense.
One of the things I said in that article
is it It's kind of a cheesy story, but
when we started um
building the storage system at Dropbox,
the team was called the Magic Pocket
team cuz that was a silly code name for
the for the for the system we built.
And so the team was oriented around
building that system. But as soon as we
shipped it,
I renamed the team to the storage team.
And that
actually took a bit of work cuz you have
to like rename all the email addresses
and the channels and the repos and the
things. And so it seems like a waste of
time. And um
but my argument to the team was
that the responsibility of the storage
team is not to advocate for Magic
Pocket, the storage system. It's to
solve the needs of storage for the
organization, right? Because who else in
the company knows more about storage
than the storage team, right? And if
there was a point in time where S3 was a
better idea,
it would make sense to move back. Or
maybe there was a different kind of
storage system that you were meant to
use, right? It's the job of the storage
team to advocate for moving back, right?
And so I've seen before, you have like a
team called the
the Puppet team, you know, if the
people don't really use Puppet that much
anymore, but like for you know, the the
Puppet the the job manager or Puppet
versus Chef, and then they'd be kind of
advocating for their team's thing, when
really a team should be oriented around
what problem do they solve? They should
not care about
the system that survives. Because if if
if you are on the magic pocket team,
and someone says we should move back to
S3, that's pretty threatening to your
identity and to your career,
right?
But are you If you're on the storage
team,
and it turns out it makes sense to move
back, I don't think that's the case, but
um
then that's an exciting new product for
you to own.
And so I think it's it seems like such
silly management philosophy, but I think
it's really really important to orient a
team and an identity around solving a
problem and not owning and defending a
system. Cuz you just see this in in big
companies, it's just
inertia is so strong. Yeah, and you see
people doing things they don't believe
in cuz that's just what they do.
If the inertia is so strong, how did you
fight it and close down all those
projects?
I think I got lucky
in so far as I was there pretty early
on. And I worked hard enough,
you know, I was putting in probably
16-hour days at the start. I'm not
advocating for that, but I was like I
was dedicating my life to to the
company, and I think it became pretty
obvious to people that I cared, you
know? It This is This is Here's a guy
over here that really wants to do the
right thing and cares about the company.
At that point, you build up enough
confidence capital, you know,
that you feel comfortable saying things.
You know, I wasn't at that point I
wasn't afraid for my career. I just I
was afraid for the wrong decisions
getting made. So, I So, So, I felt, you
know, psychologically comfortable making
those observations and then at certain
point you um
you know, that there's another you know
A lot of engineers so at one point I
would mentor
you know, all the a lot of the staff
plus engineers at the company and and
people would sometimes get grumpy, you
know, cuz they were like, "Oh,
we're not doing the right thing over
here or this is inefficient." And every
every engineer listening to this has a
story like this. They're annoyed about
some inefficiency at the company. And my
response was generally like,
"Do you think we should solve this
problem right now?"
Cuz if we should, let me know the team
to take some engineers off
and the product to shut down and I can
redirect and we can solve this problem
right now.
And they'll be like, "Oh, well,
we shouldn't shut down any other stuff."
I'm like, "Cool, well, we just have this
many engineers right now." And and so,
if there's anything higher lower
priority, let's stop doing the lower
priority thing and do the higher
priority thing, this thing. And often
times the answer was, "Oh, no, nothing
else is lower priority."
And then the answer is we just have to
accept. Just have to accept, right?
There's no point in being angry or upset
that we're not doing the right thing all
the time. So, I think there's a
dimension to you break it, you bought
it. I don't think
like when I said part of my job was
shutting products down, it wasn't going
around just causing problems, right?
It's ideally like solving problems.
Like, "Oh, this product is not going the
right direction. Let's redirect it and
do this alternative thing." And so, I
think the thing that helped me, I guess,
was was having a a sense of ownership
that like instead of
complaining
I just wanted to go fix problems. And
that was but that was part of the
culture. I mean, there was
when I started at Dropbox
and um
I remember being at Dropbox and infra
was I don't know seven, eight, nine
people.
And you know, we have someone join
from Google, for example, and they'd
say, "Well, someone should go build I
can't do anything without
this logging framework. Couldn't
possibly do anything without this
logging framework." And I'm like, "Well,
we're going okay without it." So, and
then like someone needs to build this
thing. And everyone would be like,
"Well, who is someone?" Right? Because
it's just us. It's just us. We we build
it or we don't build it. And they'd
pretty quickly
come to understand, "Oh, wait, it's just
us. It's just we There's There's no
other idiots out there. We're the
idiots." Right? So, that was I don't
know. I loved I loved that time because
it was just a
uh time of accountability that
life gets easier and harder when you
realize that everyone else is not an
idiot.
When you realize everyone else is just
dealing with their own stuff, right?
>> [laughter]
>> And so, I think um
I I do not think someone will have good
luck going around complaining about
stuff and and just saying this is a dumb
idea and being negative. I think people
will have a um
Everyone wants problems solved, though.
So, if you're someone in an organization
who is who's willing to put their head
up and say, "You know what? I think this
thing over here is a bad idea,
but here's a different idea and I'm
willing to own it and put the effort
behind it." I think that's a that's a
recipe for success. From that article,
you had a great quote or I guess a great
question to think through this. It said
you went to everyone or a bunch of
people and you would say "If we could be
spending these resources working on any
project at the company right now, would
this still be the best use of time?" And
I feel like it frames exactly what you
just described really cleanly. Yeah, I
mean I guess this is like maybe a a
trick for being a tech lead or a manager
is
almost nothing's a yes or no question.
It's a like it's a prioritization
question. Yeah, it's not like should we
redesign the database? I don't know,
maybe. I guess. Is it the most important
thing to do right now? No. Cool, let's
not do it. Right? I think it's much
easier to have those conversations than
to think about it as a yes or no. You
know, I often hear like, "Oh, my VP
won't let me do blah."
Okay. Well, it could be that your VP is
dumb, but it's probably not, right? It
could be that your VP has a different
set of priorities. Maybe their VP knows
that you need to ship these features and
if you don't, then the company's going
to be struggling. I don't know, but to
to really frame it around
prioritization. And the way I think
about the the career ladder for
engineers
is is I I think um some people, maybe
maybe it's not common, but think that
like being coming a senior senior
engineer means you get better at
programming.
But like I don't know. I think my
program abilities went down from like
level four onwards. You know, I think
once I got to like level four,
>> [laughter]
>> that was peak programmer for me and then
I probably went downhill from there. And
I got wiser, whatever, but I think the
real thing that happened is the scope
that I cared about increased. So at a
certain point, you're just thinking
about, "Cool, what matters most at the
company for the next five years?"
Um and
I don't think uh
junior engineer on their first year of
the job should try to do this.
Cuz you probably don't yet have the
wisdom, insight,
um knowledge to be able to make a good
assessment. And I think it probably
would be a mistake to be like to try to
come up with like
redirecting company strategy. But as you
grow, I think the real key part about
growing is
the the the IC 678 engineers are not
necessarily the best programmers. It's
they're just getting better at having
broad perspective
in decisions within a company.
OpenAI, Anthropic, Cursor, and Vercel
all use this product to make their lives
better. And the problem it solves is
when you're building SaaS or an AI
product and you want to sell to other
companies, there's all these
requirements you need to meet. There's
SSL, there's SCIM, there's RBAC, there's
audit logs. These are all things that
take time to integrate, but aren't the
main focus of your app. WorkOS is an API
layer that lets you meet all of these
requirements in just a few lines of
code. So, let's say you have a new SaaS
product and you want to sell to other
companies, WorkOS will solve all of
these critical feature gaps for you.
You can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast. You
mentioned this idea of do the right
thing and then, you know, the byproduct
you also get promoted. And I think
that's that's the dream. You know, do
the right thing, get promoted. But in
reality, often times people would have
to make the trade-off. Imagine a
two-by-two matrix of doing the right
thing, doing the wrong thing,
getting promoted, not getting promoted.
Obviously, the, you know, do the right
thing, get promoted, great. Do the wrong
thing, don't get promoted, obviously
bad. But I'm curious about the other two
quadrants. Which one would you have
picked when you were earlier in your
career? Let's say I came to you, I said,
"Hey, you can do the wrong thing, but
you're going to get promoted. Or you can
do the right thing and I guarantee
you're not going to get promoted. Which
one?"
>> one. Absolutely the second the second
one. So, I'm going to say a really tacky
thing, right? Um
there are a set of engineers
um
who at a certain point just make
infinity money. Like, the amount of
money they can make, you know, going and
whatever, going to work at Anthropic is
is a huge amount of money, right? And
so, there's a certain point where it
just doesn't matter anymore. Like the
money is whatever, right? But so that So
if you really want to
if you really want to maximize long-term
income, I don't think you should try to
do that. But if you wanted to maximize
long-term income, if you get to a
certain level of experience and skill
and seniority, you've made it. That's
it. You're done. The money's fine,
right? And so I think there's this
desire amongst
junior engineers early in their career
to be kind of over optimizing for
promotion and and income and salary,
etc.
as opposed to investing in themselves.
And I guess it's it's They probably
don't want to hear me say this cuz it's
easier for me as an old old guy to say
this, right? But But I think
you know, for the longest time at
Dropbox, there was a time at Dropbox
where like we just didn't have our level
system right. I was tech leading the
team and I was making the least amount
of money of the team. I'm cuz I was at
some point a technical manager, I saw
everyone's salaries. I was making the
least I think the least money. But
whatever, right? It all worked out in
the end, right? Now that was a happy
story, but I do really think
I benefit so much from working with the
best people. Like if you have two
choices, like
making 20% more money now or working
with like the best people in the world,
right? Just be around the best people
because like you will be
that's going to sit you on like the on
the ship to success, right? And now not
everyone wants to do that. Not everyone
wants to go on that Like it's there's no
shame in just wanting to be have a
regular job and just be chilling and
just be getting paid and fine.
There's There's nothing wrong with that.
But if you do want to maximize If you
want to maximize your career growth,
then the way to maximize that is to
maximize your skills, right? Like if
And And hopefully you're not so cynical
to think that there is no correlation
between talent and compensation.
Um
I don't
I If you think that's the case, okay, um
I don't know what to say. But But But
But there is a correlation between
talent and compensation and growth. And
so, my advice to people early in their
career is land at the best company with
the best people doing the most important
problems, and your life will be great.
Cuz we are so lucky as engineers. Like
What What What else could What else can
you work solving problems for a job?
Like solving puzzles for a job and
getting paid so [snorts] well. Like
engineers get paid so well compared to
most jobs. Um
the privilege that the real privilege
that we get is to work on something
cool.
And uh that's what I advocate for.
I love the idea you mentioned earlier
that's kind of counter to the common
opinion I I often hear. Like the common
opinion I hear they someone working at a
big company, they're in this machine,
that it's kind of defeatist. They're
going, "Ah, I ship this thing, but I
hate this or I don't believe in this."
And the I I really liked your
perspective on you know, doing the right
thing and like
basically giving a damn that
you know, someone outside of you is
doing the right thing, too, and
expanding your sense of ownership. And I
want to know what is your motivation for
that cuz there's so many other people
who are faced with the same inputs, and
they get to a very different conclusion.
So, what motivates you to actually do
the right thing when
the machine doesn't necessarily
incentivize you to do so? Yeah.
Well, I think the machine does
incentivize you to do so, but I don't
think it's it's visible
immediately. Like I think people who
sample who who do less job hopping
really do grow the most because I would
I would say very strongly, if you're not
in a job for 3 years, you're not going
to see
whether your decisions were good. Like
you you can get more money as a junior
engineer, but you cannot become a senior
a very talented senior engineer without
being around for long enough to own the
consequences of your decisions.
It's Yeah, it's like it's like playing a
basketball game and leaving before the
game's over. Like, you're just not
learning, right? So So
I do think there's an actual structural
incentive towards staying in a job. Now,
if you're in a bad job, leave the bad
job, right? But there's a structural
incentive to be able to stay long enough
to have an impact.
But also, I don't know. I like
again, I guess it's easy for me to say.
And also, I joined the tech industry
when it wasn't like a very lucrative
field. Like it you know, it
it wasn't like it is now, you know? But
I just like it. The reason I left
academia
was because I wasn't confident I was
making the right So what would happen
how I would how I was in academia, I'm
not saying everyone was like this, but
you So firstly, you you don't know what
to do.
So you have to make up a problem to
solve. And then you make up a problem.
And then you make up a solution.
You know, and hopefully a good one.
And then you write a paper where you try
to convince everyone that was a really
good idea.
>> [laughter]
>> And I hated it cuz I didn't want to
convince people. I just wanted to build
it
and see if it was good. Like I just
wanted to build it and ship it and see I
didn't want to
play pretends and and argue about it was
good. Um that's what makes me feel good.
I don't know. And like obviously,
if you're a engineer who's living
paycheck to paycheck,
you should maybe ignore what I'm saying.
Like I don't want to come across as
unempathetic to anyone who's really
struggling financially.
But if you are not struggling
financially,
the
best thing you can do for your quality
of life
is
you know, in me enjoying what you do
every day.
You know, like I don't know, you could
have a fancier car
or you can enjoy what you do every day.
And I love cars, like I'm a I'm a motor
head, but I promise that enjoying what
you do every day is going to have a much
bigger impact on your life. And um
personally, I don't enjoy like going to
work and and working on projects I don't
believe in. Like I can only
operate. And so you Jamie, my
co-founder, is the same way. Like
we we really get along really well in
this respect.
We can only um
we can only put up with doing things we
actually care about and
and believe in.
And I think
that's that's the luxury That's more
luxury than taking a first-class flight.
That's more luxury than going to a
three-Michelin-star restaurant.
The luxury is you don't get up and have
to do a a terrible job, you know, um you
get up and go to a place that you like
your co-workers and you solve cool
problems and you go home and feel proud
of yourself.
If you can If you can construct your
career that way, and it's not easy, you
have to it's it requires very active
effort, then you're going to have a good
life.
I I saw on your career journey
it said that you're occasional manager
and you you seem like someone who really
enjoys the the technical aspects of
things. So, how did you decide to
occasionally dip into management?
I feel
like most people should not want to be
managers.
And I sometimes think it's a bit of a
red flag if someone wants to be a
manager too much, right?
Cuz um being a manager is a hard job.
And uh so I think most people should go
into management because they need to.
Cuz it's necessary. And so what happened
every time I went into management, I'm
in a management role now as well, cuz
you have to, right? Um
but um
we someone needed to manage the team.
And and so I do genuinely enjoy
accountability. I like responsibility. I
like
I like um having weight on my shoulders,
I I suppose.
And so I went into management
several times.
Uh but as soon as I had the opportunity
to get out, as soon as someone else
would come in and manage the team, I
would I would kind of bounce out of that
role back into engineering. Um
Now, going to management is is is
tremendously educational.
If um
being a manager really lets you see the
world in a different way. You realize
companies are more complicated than you
thought. You realize the engineers are
more complicated than you thought. You
realize everyone on the team is going
through something. And you And you
realize, "Oh, wow, now I understand why
that thing happened." Um so, being a
manager is very educational.
One thing I would say I would strongly
caution people against is going into
management too early in their career.
And I see this happen um
I see this happen a lot with
well-intentioned people
who want to push people into management
as a means of career advancement, right?
I think it's doing people a disservice.
I think you should let folks take their
time
in an organiza- in a in a career
journey. I don't think you should be
going into management
under most circumstances in the first 3
years of your career. I think you should
get to
ideally get to staff engineer before you
do that. That's not going to happen for
everybody, but ideally you take the time
because if you go into management before
you're excellent technician,
it will limit your ability to influence
strategy later in your career. How does
that play out? It plays out with people
who um who uh
uh
stuck or have roles as people managers
where, you know, they they see their job
as making maybe making a team happy
or maybe coordinating a team
um or, you know, dealing with all the
day-to-day
um
challenges of like people on a team, but
they're not
organizational leaders.
They're not like pushing the team
towards excellence. They They're not
like, "Hey, how can we reframe what this
team is about? How can we, you know,
help influence technical strategy? And
um
again, people management is a fine job,
but I think
um the best companies are ones where all
the managers are very technical. And so,
they're able to make sure the company's
doing like at a certain point like if
you're not
not a particularly technical manager,
you're not going to be able to evaluate
the work of your team. You're not going
to know whether your team is even doing
well. And I guess maybe you might
contribute towards some of the stuff you
were saying about, you know, cynical
organizational attitudes where like my
manager doesn't understand me. Maybe
your manager doesn't understand you
>> [laughter]
>> if they haven't spent enough time
developing technical skills and and and
and and struggling. Yeah, there's uh
another uh piece that you wrote I
thought was really good about, you know,
leading by example and you actually say
it's bad to lead by example, but um
there there's a quote in there. It says,
"Modern tech workers can be an
anti-authoritarian bunch at the best of
times." And
let's say you're a a tech lead or tech
lead manager or manager, you know, how
how do you strike that balance so you
don't lose credibility as a tech lead?
Yeah, there there are command and
control companies
that like the manager just tells people
to do things and they just do them.
Those typically are not excellent
companies. And not every company needs
to be excellent, but if you want to have
a company where
the team's really innovating, like the
engineers feel very personally
responsible for making really
high-quality decisions,
you have to have them believe in what
you're doing.
And so, you you know, at Convex, I'm the
founder and CTO.
I can't really go to someone's desk and
say do this thing.
Now, they they might do it just cuz they
like me. There's a good chance they
would do it, but not because I'm the
boss. They'd be like, "Well, why?"
Right? And that's that's because that's
our culture. I mean, we don't just do
things cuz we're told. Like if I want
someone to do something, I'll spend time
with the team talking about why we're
doing it. Where Where the market's
trending? Where's the gap in our
product? What, you know? And then once
we've really well articulated
um why something matters, people are
just going to do it anyway. Now, now
there's a Sometimes you have to have
hard conversations, but I think um
the way I think about it in terms of
certainly in terms of conflict in an
organization, there's like this kind of
hierarchy of of the values you have, and
then why, what, and how.
And engineers are very often debating
the how. They're very often debating
like what algorithm should we use for
this? And like, you know, should we use
this container service or that container
service? And these are kind of like the
implementation details.
But most times when I see organizational
conflict, it's because well-intentioned
people
uh debating as best they can about how
to do something, but they don't agree on
why we're doing it.
So, if if one team thinks the most
important thing we can do right now is
get more features out to expand our
customer base, and the other team thinks
the most important thing we can do is
increase reliability cuz there's a risk
to the business, right? They're both
very valid perspectives, but it's going
to lead to them doing very different
things.
And within an organization, I'm a strong
believer that everyone needs to have
100% why alignment. So, the stuff we
argue about or we debate or we talk
about ad nauseam is why.
And then largely I just trust the team
to do the right thing.
Um and I think that's the case for any
in any tech lead. If you want to have
credibility on a team,
it's not If you think that you can just
tell someone to do something and they'll
listen to me cuz I'm the senior guy, and
no, they won't. They won't. If they
listen to me, it's cuz I've come in and
explained it in a way that resonates
with them. And again, one of my jobs at
Dropbox was to resolve the situations.
You know, someone would say, "Oh, that
team's an idiot. They won't do blah
this." And then I would go talk to that
team. That team was not an idiot, right?
And we talked through it, and they would
decide to do the project. And it wasn't
because
they were scared of me. I hope they
weren't at least. It was because, you
know, I take the time to figure out what
their motivations are. And And that's
something you really have to learn. If
you're a tech lead, you don't really
have that much authority over people.
And really you have to kind of encourage
them and get them to believe in what
you're doing.
Um And if you are leading through
authority, you're not going to have a
culture where good ideas arise from
within the org. People are just going to
do what they're told.
Influence without authority is huge, and
I think there's I mean, even big
companies like Meta, they technically
don't have titles. Everyone's just a
software engineer. Um Is that also how
Convoy is run? I mean, we're We're a
very flat organization. There are people
in tech lead roles.
I don't completely buy that everyone's a
software engineer thing. It's like, you
know, at I I is
you know, at Dropbox, everyone's a
member of technical staff. Because it's
kind of like a wink wink thing. You kind
of know. It's like no one's mentioned
the title, but you kind of know if like
the most senior person in the company
comes to your desk, you're probably
going to notice, you know? And uh and so
I think there's no point in in in, you
know, playing pretends. People People
know, you know? But I will say that you
should have a organizational culture
where you don't do something just
because a senior person says something.
Now, I do think that reputation matters.
Like I certainly think that, you know, I
don't know. If If If a If a very
experienced person at a company comes
and tries to explain something to you,
you probably should listen to them
because they probably have some wisdom.
There might be something to be learned
there. You should be open to it. But
ultimately, um
yeah, even even the most senior person I
don't think um
should be leading through authority.
They They
They They should use the benefit of
their experience to be able to to win
the hearts and minds. And and that's how
you in engineering culture is so
important. And if you want a culture of
of ownership and innovation and and
drive and enthusiasm and people trying
to do the right thing not get promoted,
right? You have to have a culture where
everyone believes in what they're doing.
And no one's going to believe in what
they're doing if the senior principal
engineer comes to the desk and says,
"I'm not going to tell you why but you
have to delete this database and do this
other thing."
And no, that that's not an empowering
statement. What the empowering statement
is, "Hey, let's spend some time together
to talk about where this product's
trending and how this is probably not
going to work out and how there might be
a different way we can solve this
problem." Uh on the topic of tech
leadership, I mean, in that article I
mentioned that you know, the title was
don't lead by example. And I think that
kind of might be confusing for people.
Can you explain why you think you
shouldn't lead by example? Yeah,
leadership by example is a very passive
thing to do. And engineers are passive
people at the best of times. You know, I
think uh that's that's stereotypically a
little bit part of their personality. Um
so, I mean, the the very concrete
example is, you know, when I first
started becoming an engineering leader,
I was trying to lead by example. So, I I
wanted to kind of um
demonstrate the behaviors that I want
everyone else to have. And very
specifically, like um
with regards to on-call and people
getting paged, I want people I want
people to have high ownership. I want
people to jump on issues as soon as it
happened. So, I would do it. I'd be
always the first one to respond to a
page. I would always be like, you know,
writing up the reports. I would always
be jumping on all the bugs and stuff.
And and like really falling over myself
to kind of show how I want people to do
to be.
But from their perspective, all they see
is that the the lead's just doing all
these jobs. And they don't know they're
like, "Oh, maybe that's James's job." Or
maybe James knows how to do it it, I
don't know how to do it. Um
Turns out I didn't know. I was just kind
of figuring out. Or you maybe he likes
doing those things. And I think at a
certain point
being a leader is about understanding
human psychology.
And I don't think you can just act
a certain way in front of people and
wait for them to copy you, right? I
think you should obviously you should
act with integrity and values, and you
should you should you know, you
shouldn't you should own the values of
the team. But you have sometimes have to
explain stuff. Sometimes you have to
tell people, "Hey,
and very very very specifically
there's a there's a there's a trajectory
almost every leader goes through.
Every high-achieving leader where they
become a tech lead, and they care so
much that they become a micromanager.
Like they review every line of code,
they're involved in every decision. And
at a certain point, um
they are the bottleneck for the team. So
this person is so overwhelmed, you might
have gone through this yourself, you
know? They're so overwhelmed, and
they're like, "Wait, my team doesn't
even seem busy right now, and I'm so
busy. I'm reviewing all this code, I'm
doing the strategy. What's going on?"
And then a manager will come along and
say, "Hey, like you're micromanaging.
You got to let your team have more
ownership."
And so
the tech lead says, "Okay, sure.
Whatever. I'll let them own stuff." And
they'll just take their hands off the
wheel, and then the team falls apart,
right?
>> [laughter]
>> Because you can't just stop doing the
things you're doing, right? You have to
go and have a conversation with people.
And so and so I I see it I see
leadership as this kind of slider
between oversight and accountability.
So when when someone's new to the team,
when they're very junior, they're in a
mode of oversight. Like you're checking
their work, right? But at a certain
point, you have to dial down the
oversight, and very importantly, dial up
the accountability. So instead of
saying, "I'm not going to look at what
you're doing anymore," you say, "Okay,
cool. You've got this project. Let me
know when it's going to get done. Next
Thursday? Cool. All right. What's the
plan? This is going to happen? Okay, how
are you going to know it's correct?
Great, great, great. It's on you.
I expect you to do that. Great. Let me
Let me know if there's any issues,
right? And then the the ownership
relationship is explicitly on them.
Because what you want to do is basically
encourage ownership within teams.
You can't go from owning something
yourself yourself to not owning
something yourself [laughter]
and expect that to develop. You have to
go have those conversations. You have to
go and give people accountability. Now,
what I have found,
even though that can feel like an
awkward conversation, most people
genuinely like accountability.
Most people like to own their work. Most
people like to say, "Hey, this is on
you.
We're going to We're all going down with
the ship, right? If [laughter] this you
know
I'm not going to leave you high and dry.
Like, you know, I'm the tech lead. I
still take, you know, responsibility
too.
You're accountable to this project.
And uh go for it. And that's how you can
develop people in your team. You know, a
tech lead shouldn't be about you as the
boss and the team is like the people
who, you know, do the work or something,
right? It's about this kind of flow
where you're the more experienced person
typically, maybe the more organized
person, the more strategic person, and
you're working on developing your team
members so they can take your job.
And then you can do something else.
That slider you mentioned, what if you
give someone accountability and they
blow it? Do they go back down the slider
to, you know, where you start
micromanaging?
>> to recognize it, right? So,
this is growth. I mean, this is growth,
right? It doesn't always work. And so,
um
I think I had another article about um
paper cuts or something. So, you know,
we'd call these paper cuts, you know, so
um some decisions don't matter that
much. You know, you get them wrong and
maybe it sets you back a week. You get
them wrong and maybe something's a bit
suboptimal. And these are great
candidates to give people accountability
for because they do it and if it doesn't
work,
they get to experience it and it will
feel bad. And
I guess that's good. It's It's good to
feel bad. You know, you shouldn't be
demoralized, but it's good to try
something and it doesn't work and you're
like, "Oh, wow, that's that that didn't
work." And that you And then you feed
that back into your little, you know,
LLM in your brain and you get better
next time, right? Uh that's that's a
growth experience. I think what you
don't want to let people do is like lose
their arm. You know, like like paper
cuts are fine, but I would not let
someone a junior person, especially,
design the replication system at Convex
or whatever. Like, you know, you have to
have safeguards and and one of the arts
as a CTO or leader or tech lead is
figuring out the right level of altitude
for how to know whether you can trust
someone to take on ownership for
something. You mentioned, because you
were the most senior engineer at Dropbox
at some point, that you had to mentor
other very senior engineers. And
you know, when I think about mentoring a
junior engineer, it's relatively
straightforward patterns. But when I
think about, let's say I need to uh
mentor a senior staff engineer or maybe
even a a principal engineer, how do you
mentor someone like that that's already
so polished? They already know how to
take ownership. Um yeah, how do you
mentor someone so senior? Yeah, I mean,
this in two ways. One One is there is
still just a whole bunch of commonality.
Everyone goes through the same problems.
They They don't know how to deliver
harsh feedback. They
They don't know, you know,
there is a bunch of the standard stuff
people working on. But I do think that
um
that at a certain point everyone needs
to become the best version of
themselves. Sounds so cheesy, right? But
there is not an archetype for what,
according to me, there's not an
archetype for a senior principal
engineer.
There's you've got to be your own brand
of engineer, right? So, you might be for
me I'm like the strategic kind of
collaboration simplicity abstraction
engineer, and my coding just fell off a
cliff, you know? Some engineers are like
the the deep uh science fiction you
know, the super hardcore science you
know, problem solving engineer. So,
everyone's going to find their own
brand. So, often times what I'll be
working on them is is a combination of
two things. One, finding their their
strengths and helping them
be more spiky, helping them to to like
really um
excel in the area that makes them
special.
At the same time,
almost always working on the personal
side of being engineering. Like the the
organizational personal understanding
people, understanding the why. It's just
I don't know. We're we're so mathy, you
know, as an industry. We think that
somehow like even silly things like like
for example I have to tell so many
senior engineers
that you can't change someone's mind in
a meeting.
You just can't do it. Like you can you
can you can disagree with someone, and
they're going to be mad or whatever,
right? But like but to change someone's
mind involves going through a complex
series of like of
neurological processes, right? That like
that don't happen live in front of 10
people in a meeting, right? And so, if
you force someone to agree with you
about them being wrong, they're just
going to go along with it. And and the
ego is going to get bruised and
whatever. So, so one thing, you know,
firstly meetings aren't generally aren't
for decision making.
Most of the time when you identify
uh a disagreement, I would point out the
disagreement and why
and why I I don't agree or you know,
where the problems are, provide enough
information, and then let it sit, and
let them go and reflect on it, and like
come back and have a conversation a week
later after they've after they've gone
back and forth about the why, right? And
this this kind of a lot of very
psychological, but it's it's it makes no
sense to be like, well, they should be
able to change their mind. I mean, well,
they won't, right? That team should do
this, well, they didn't, right? You
know, people should like my API, well,
they don't, right? And [snorts] I think
it's like that whole like it's almost um
it's almost like a capital
a capitalist attitude towards like
interpersonal behaviors, right? It's
like doesn't like you know capitalism
success, you know, or or or impact. It
doesn't matter how well-intentioned you
were if you didn't manage to convince
them. That you could be the smartest
person in the world, but if you can't
change someone's mind, then you are kind
of useless, right? And so I think it is
a lot of senior engineers still struggle
with this. It doesn't matter how smart
you are, it doesn't matter how right you
are. Are you effective? And a lot of
being effective at that level is about
you know, uncertainty and project
management and simplicity blah blah blah
blah blah, but also kind of
interpersonal dynamics because most hard
problems happen with a team.
Not always, but generally when you're at
that level, you're going to have to have
10 20 people working with you to get
something done, and that that's a whole
different ballgame.
On the topic of career advice, the the
industry's changed a lot in the last 5
years because of all these agentic
tools, and I wanted to know if you
thought is there any career advice that
majorly changed in the last 5 years?
Something that you used to say 5 years
ago, you don't say anymore, or vice
versa.
No, I I I don't know if I've changed my
perspective much, but I think the
industry has changed its perspective
dramatically. I think um I mean, let's
just let's just be honest about it. Um
there is incredible demand in Silicon
Valley for senior engineers, and it is
getting harder for junior engineers to
succeed and grow.
Um for a variety of reasons. Um, why is
there demand for senior engineers? Well,
because LLMs can't do everything. Well,
you know, the architecture and
simplicity and design, they're still the
domain of human beings, despite what you
might hear on Twitter, right? And every
company, including the labs, are
desperately hiring senior engineers,
right?
But, junior tasks are getting a little
bit commoditized, and that worries me.
Because, I do think that, um,
that learning, it's very, you know,
wisdom is kind of facts
put into practice and then synthesized,
you know? And so,
a lot of people would argue that, oh,
well, you know, it's easy to learn now
because of ChatGPT, because you can just
go ask it a question about
how does two-phase commit work, or
what's the difference between snapshot
isolation and serializability, and it
will give you a probably a pretty good
answer.
But, I think growth as an engineer
does require wisdom.
And wisdom only really happens when you
synthesize it, in my, my opinion. And
so, I think, um,
I'm still very bullish on young people.
We're hiring junior engineers at Convex.
I'm very excited about, I mean, I love
working with junior engineers who are
really hungry to grow.
But, what I would say is, train your
mind. Like,
do not listen to anyone who tells you
that there is an advantage to having
less knowledge. Yeah, I'm, I'm not sure
if you've seen people will say these
ludicrous things that like, oh, maybe in
the future, like, not knowing
engineering will be an advantage cuz you
won't have biases and you'll just use
Claude. I think these are like ludicrous
statements. Like, like,
software engineering is an intellectual
discipline that helps you think, like,
like, the software engineering, the best
software engineering is not about
knowing syntax, and it's not about
knowing an algorithm. It's being really
good at conceptualizing problems and
being able to break them down to
building blocks and coming up with clean
solutions to them.
And that requires experience. It
requires
like it's like doing doing weights with
your mind. And just like if you went to
the gym and you just like
it never hurt. Like if you went to the
gym and just picked up really light
weights,
um you're not growing. And also, if you
went to the gym and picked up a heavy
weight and like, "Okay, cool. I think I
can do it." and then you let the robot
pick up the weight for you there, you're
also not really growing, right? You have
to do the reps. And so, I would say, and
it's tough,
but find a way to
stress your brain
every day.
Find a way to to avoid
Now, obviously a genetic coding is here,
right? Obviously that's, you know, I
could never tell someone to like never
use the coding agent cuz that'd be
silly, you know? But I can say that it
is easy
to fall into a passivity trap, like when
you're just being passive about your
learning. And I do think you need to
spend some time in the
intellectual wilderness of not being
able to solve a problem and struggling.
If you I I I would say if you're running
into a a new um
a new problem, try to think of a
solution yourself and then go check with
an LLM.
It's going to
be hard for you. It's almost like
for example,
I'm not very good at reading anymore. I
got to be honest. Like I would find it
hard I mean, I can read, obviously, but
I find it hard to sit down and read a
book because my brain has been fried by
the stimulation economy, right? Like
Like I Like I find it I go home and I'm
tired and I watch a YouTube video. I
don't tend to go home and read a novel.
I should be better at that.
But it takes discipline to do that. I
would say similarly,
it's getting harder to solve a difficult
problem without reaching for the help.
It's getting harder and harder every day
to be faced with a very difficult
intellectual problem and not be like,
"Well, I'll just I'll just do a Google
search or I'll just ask Claude." You
know, whatever. I'm still doing the
work. Uh I don't know. I I would really
encourage people to practice
using your brain every day.
If I was just devil's advocate or just
thinking from the junior engineer
perspective, I might think, "Well, the
proof that Claude can do this work today
means that I don't need to know it today
or tomorrow or in the future. So, why
why even build that skill in the first
place? Like and also these agentic
tools, they have positive trajectories,
too. So,
Yes. So, firstly, um
the agents are not particularly good at
a lot of parts of engineering currently.
Um and so, probably everyone should
agree there's, you know,
Claude is not good at designing
distributed systems protocols right now,
for example. You know, or or managing a
a 3 million line code base, you know. Um
and so, there are parts of engineering
where engineers are valuable. And like I
said, you know this because the labs are
all hiring engineers. No matter what
they say, they're still hiring
engineers, right? Desperately hiring
engineers. Um really, really
aggressively hiring engineers.
Um
so, engineers still have value.
And maybe they won't in the future, but
I doubt it. I really do think there's a
role for human ingenuity in engineering.
And so, here's the here's the trade-off
I would pose to people. I mean, there's
there's kind of three paths. One, get
out. Get out of engineering, go mow
lawns, and do whatever if you want.
That's the that's the most nihilistic
attitude. I I don't believe in that. I
believe I really love engineering and I
believe that there's promising roles for
human beings in engineering.
So, the second is
to realize that um
there's value right now for humans in
engineering. And maybe one day AGI will
be here.
Let's say in a year's time AGI will be
here.
And there's two people.
One person just gave up on
problem-solving right now, and they're
just like
feeding the machine, and they're running
17 coding agents in parallel, and
they're just accepting everything Claude
says, and they've given up.
Right? And one person said, "You know
what? I still want to have an active
role in my learning. I want to
understand what it's doing. I want to
think hard about problem-solving."
Right?
Play it out 1 year, AGI arrives. Who is
going to be better placed for the
future?
Right?
The person who's been training their
mind. Right? Like there was there's
you don't Engineering's not a means to
an end. It's a mechanism for for
improving your mental processes. It's
It's like like I still do whiteboarding
coding interviews. And by the way,
Anthropic still does whiteboarding
coding interviews. Just in case you were
wondering, they don't say like just use
Claude. Right? So, I still do white
whiteboarding coding interviews with
candidates.
Candidates are getting worse at coding.
That's absolutely true.
But I don't know any better vehicle for
evaluating someone's intellectual
capacity for problem-solving than seeing
them solve an engineering problem.
Right? It's a It's a great mechanism for
doing so. It's like you know,
um
if you were doing a math degree,
right?
A big part of doing advanced mathematics
is proving theorems.
And by the way, the theorems are already
all proven, right? When
part of the you know, the exams and is
proving a theorem that has already been
proven. And so, you might say, "Well,
what's the point of proving that
theorem? It's already been done." Well,
the point is that the act of proving
that theorem
improves your mind. Right? And then you
can go and do more innovative stuff. So,
I would say sh
Sure, you may not I still do think that
there is a very very promising role for
human beings in engineering. Maybe not
in coding, but coding and engineering
are very different things. right? Um,
but even if you don't believe me, you
can either give up now, but or you can
just keep trying to improve your brain
and you'll be better off anyway. Imagine
if you're wrong. Imagine if you take the
defeatist view. Imagine if you say,
"Well, AGI is coming next week. Why
bother doing anything?" And imagine
you're wrong.
Oh my god, you just got off the
You just got off the
>> [laughter]
>> off the ride. You got off the ride.
There's so much cool stuff. I mean, this
is a cool time for engineering, right?
This is a really cool time. There's so
much cool stuff happening. And I don't
And I I I hate this talk about like
AI means humans don't have a role
anymore. AI means no one's going to have
a job. AI means we're going to do
nothing else new and there's no one's
going to I What I like is, "Hey, look at
this all this new cool stuff we can
build."
Like, look at how there's ways we can
make people's lives better. And to be
honest, I really wish my peers and and
and my cohort would stop it with the
the real doomer like um
human elimination kind of narrative and
because I think there is a little bit of
a like a
you know, a psychological anchoring, you
know?
I and as part of Convex want to make the
you know, we didn't start Convex to
eliminate jobs. We started Convex
because we want to make it easier for
people to build cool stuff. And And I
think the more we as an industry get
behind, let's do everything we can to
make it possible for people to do more
cool things.
I think it's a really exciting future we
have ahead of us. I wanted to talk about
what you're working on now or Convex and
why did you quit Dropbox to build
Convex? I Dropbox is a great place. At a
certain point I I was there eight years.
Uh
whether I I don't know if I say I
outgrew the company, but I'd been the
most senior engineer for a while there.
Um
you know, at a certain point I
I wanted to grow and do my own stuff,
you know? And so So I left the company
in very amicably. Um, and um,
started Convex. Now, why Convex? Convex
started pre-agentic era.
Cuz my observation was that that um,
the real differentiator in the success
of a project, especially a large
project, is the quality of the
abstractions, the quality of the design,
the quality of the architecture, right?
Systems that thrive over time and are
extensible are systems that are
architected well.
And in my mind, the most difficult
challenge in engineering, according to
me, is distributed state management. How
do we store state reliably and reason
about it, you know, modifying it
concurrently with other users? And so,
so we designed um, a platform for
application building based on our
experiences building large-scale
systems. So, Convex is a is a
transactional database where the
transactions are written in TypeScript.
They run as stored procedures,
TypeScript stored procedures, they're
serializable. There's, you know,
automatic reactivity. So, what the
client sees is a consistent view of
what's on the on the server.
And I would say Convex is a very
designed platform cuz Convex is designed
to be very composable and fit together
well.
And so, we designed Convex for
developers to use. In particular, we
wanted to make it so that application
developers were able to build complex
full-stack applications. That was the
goal of Convex. Now, all of a sudden,
agentic development came along.
And that's been really interesting for
us because it turns out
that um,
what humans find hard is also what
agents find hard. You know,
you know, the coding agents are not
particularly good with large
code bases, they're not particularly
good with um, reasoning about um, action
at a distance, you know, race conditions
across services, they're not
particularly good at simple
architectures over time. And these are
the things that Convex gives you as a
developer. So, the idea now and and
almost everyone using Convex is using
Convex because they have the coding
agent doing their front end, but they
need
a back end abstraction, a higher level
abstraction than something like AWS or
something like hosted Postgres, which
makes their problems go away. And that's
that's the company.
That was one thing I wanted to ask cuz
immediately when I think, "Oh, I just
need a back end or something like that."
Just go to AWS or, you know, just host
something like that. So, this is the
layer of abstraction on kind of on top
of those types of primitives Yes. that
makes it easier for an application
developer. It it ties into a lot of the
stuff I I said earlier about making
problems go away. And frankly, I mean, I
I watched the interview you did with
Barbara Liskov, and Barbara was my
advisor in grad school, and and I we
worked a lot together and a lot on
abstraction, and you know, the value in
clean designs that minimize complexity.
And so, AWS is a fine tool.
Postgres is a fine tool.
Although, none of the mainstream
databases are that great, frankly. But,
um
they're fine tools, but they're not
they're not make problems go away,
right? And so, the idea of Convex is a
higher level set of abstractions that
you can use and not reason about state
management, not reason about
concurrency, not reason about
scheduling, not reason about
transactions,
uh not reason about polling and data
sync and type safety and all those
things. So, Convex is a If If you think
about, you know, the history of of
engineering, over time the abstraction
floor raises. You know, when Barbara was
first starting,
she was using punch cards, you know? Um
I don't I don't know if she mentioned it
to you, but
uh when she started as a programmer, she
never heard the word programmer before,
you know?
Uh that was the first time she heard the
word, right? And then, you know, you
went from punch cards to like, you know,
having proper operating systems and and
and uh you know, then, you know,
languages like C and then higher level
languages and and then you had cloud
computing. And over time, the
abstraction floor raises, and you
largely forget about what's going on
beneath the surfaces. Most people don't
think about how S3 is implemented. I do,
but that's what I used to work on. But
like most people just use it and it just
stores your data and it gives it back
and that's great.
That's a successful abstraction. But I
do strongly believe that the world
is and has been overdue for a new
abstraction. Uh one level up the stack.
And especially now that people are doing
agent development, largely they don't
want to own a Postgres instance. Largely
they don't want to think about Kafka
versus RabbitMQ. Uh they don't want to
think about, you know, what set of tools
to use. They want it just to work so
they can focus on building their
application.
When you talk about, you know, the
abstraction, there's obviously a lot of
stuff going on behind the scenes in
Convex and the the technical side. And
I, you know, what what is it that Convex
is building behind the scenes that
you're most excited about and why?
Basically Convex is a new
operating system in some respects,
right? So we have the primitives,
queries, mutations, actions,
subscriptions.
What I think is kind of cool is how we
built this, you know, we have our own
database that we built. We own
distributed database that, you know,
does, you know, tracks read ranges and
write ranges and does very efficient um
subscriptions over web sockets, etc. So
that's that's the current operating
system set of primitives.
But um
Convex is getting much larger workloads
now and much more interesting workloads
and more high performance workloads. And
so we're in the process of developing a
slightly lower level API
for doing very efficient kind of
background processes, singletons,
APIs like fork, like you, you know, like
operating system primitives. And I'm
pretty excited about launching these and
how much is faster it's going to make
various um Convex components like the
workflow system. Um
And to be honest, the thing I find
exciting every day,
challenging every day. I I still find
Convex very hard. Like
to be honest, like
I struggle every day.
Um I don't find my job easy. I I mean I
I
I feel confident in my job, but it's not
easy. Like designing the new API for
this is super hard. I can't just go ask
ChatGPT. It's not going to give a good
answer, right? And um
cuz it's innovation. It's a It's a new
ideas. I really enjoy it. I find it um
stressful sometimes. I find it um
challenging and tiring, but I also find
it exciting. And and and I would I you
know, I would encourage engineers to try
to find this kind of stuff to work on
where it's like you're on that edge of
like I'm really liking this, but also
it's a bit tricky, you know, it's it's a
bit tough.
You mentioned fork and in operating
systems I'm familiar, you know, you just
take the existing process and kind of
split it. What's the idea of fork in a
distributed system? So, Convex almost
never has scale issues with regards to
live traffic. You know, live traffic is
like um
typically bound by user-facing
interactions, people clicking on stuff,
running website, you know, acting on
website. Every now and then someone will
come to Convex and want to kick off a
million background jobs to do something,
background processing.
It's a big workload. You
programmatically you can trigger huge
workloads, right? And so the one of
things we have to scale is is kind of
these background workloads and a lot of
them involve things like scheduling.
And there are a lot of workloads in
Convex that would be um
very efficient if you had a background
singleton process to perform things like
aggregates, you know, um
I'll give a very silly example, right?
If you have a let's say you're building
an election on Convex, a voting system,
and every vote is a new uh row in the in
the table. And you want to show a tally
of the votes.
You know, one way of doing this is
having a bunch of background processes
or crons adding these things up.
One way is doing a table scan, which is
you know, the obvious way to use
Postgres, which doesn't scale. The other
is to have a background job, which if
there's new votes, it adds them all up,
keeps a tally. If there's no new votes,
it goes to sleep and waits on like a
condition variable to wake up up to wake
up again when there's with a new job to
perform. And so these are the kind of
primitives
that we're working on right now. Most
people won't even know they exist, but
allow us to build these very
high-performance um primitives for
scheduling
um aggregates, you know, background
aggregations, etc. Um and I'm pretty
excited about like the the next
generation of workloads we can support
as a result.
When you reflect on your career and you
it sounds like you've done a lot of
gnarly technical work across your PhD,
Dropbox seemed like pretty intense
systems work, and Convex is also doing a
lot of cool stuff. When you look back on
your career, what was the most
technically stimulating work you've ever
done? And you know, why was it hard and
what did you learn from it?
There was certainly times in grad school
where we were like um formally model
modeling consensus protocols and stuff
and you know, I'd be on the phone with
Barbara on weekends and talking through
um trying to reason about this in our
heads. That was pretty intellectually
stimulating and fun. But I think the
stuff I found most stimulating was stuff
like working on very large storage
system with a team where
you know, things are going wrong. You
know, where where the rubber hits the
road, that's where I find And this is
everyday at Convex. You know, the rubber
hits the road like you know, uh hey, we
have a uh compaction process that runs
in the background, but it's running into
issues. We might have to redesign it
using
partitioning, etc.
I I feel most intellectually stimulated
where where there's a really clear
constraint in front of me.
And um
that to me is engineering. Like if
I don't actually know what the
definition of engineering is, but I'm
just going to make it up in my mind,
engineering is science with constraints.
It's like It's like how to How do you
solve problems in the presence of
resource constraints?
I'm not particularly interested in
constraint-free environments. That's
art.
I like craft and engineering. And the
the more visceral and difficult the
constraints, the more fun that is for
me.
And I I've I've been lucky enough to
I don't know whether it's luck or
intention, I don't know, but I I I've
always placed myself in those
environments, you know, like
let's go get on the hardest team and and
own the hardest problem and then
um and then, you know, put the effort
into to to survive.
This question might be a little bit off
topic, but you know, I know you were a
consultant for the show the TV show
Silicon Valley.
I love that show and I got to hear how'd
you get involved in that? Yeah, that was
a lot of fun. So, um
a lot of folks might not know this. Um
I had nothing to do with season 1. So, a
lot of TV shows, they don't know whether
they're going to survive as a TV show.
So, so, um Mike Judge who started um who
who who wrote Silicon Valley also was of
Beavis and Butt-Head and Office Space
fame. He started his career as a
software engineer at I think Lockheed or
something. So, he actually was a
software engineer that a lot of people
don't realize. And so, Silicon Valley
was like a throwback to the kind of
work he did. And if you anyone's seen
the movie Office Space, you would you
would get this. It's That's a really a,
you know, dystopian cubicle era uh tech
uh industry um film.
Um so, they did season 1 of of Silicon
Valley and then it was very popular and
they got picked up and so, they had to
figure out what to do for season 2, but
they didn't know what to do because they
did They'd written a storyline that gets
to the point where there's a compression
algorithm. And And then what happens?
And so they needed to find um
an expert on compression and I guess
ostensibly that was me. I don't I don't
know whether I was an expert on
compression. I guess I was an expert on
storage at least. And so and so they
came to the office and and uh and we
just chat chatted and it was so much
fun, you know? And so I was involved in
um you're pretty heavily involved in the
show. Um
A lot of it was you know storyline and
and so forth. So like yes, so what would
you do with the compression algorithm?
What would could you design a storage
system? And and so coming up with story
ideas that that uh technically accurate.
They were really
you'd be surprised to know how much they
care about accuracy. A lot of um
people I know can't watch that show cuz
it's just so creepily [snorts]
accurate. They find it so cringey. And
partly why Silicon Valley can this TV
show could be so cringey is because
it's it's real. Like those stories are
almost almost
I don't even know everyone. So many of
the stories in Silicon Valley are just
real stories. They're just a they went
to a bunch of companies just farmed
everyone for like stories of crazy
things that happened in the tech
industry and they wove them into the
series. And all the characters are based
on real people and and real archetypes.
Um but they also cared very much about
technical accuracy. So I would also do
technical consulting and then they'd say
stuff like oh we're
building a data center in our house.
What should the rack look like? And you
know, what should the
diagram on the wall look like? And and
partly, you know, I wanted to be like oh
well it doesn't really matter. No one's
going to care. And they're like no no
no, it matters. Like they really cared
to get it right. Um
So yeah, I love the show, but it it can
be hard to watch just because of
oh my god, how how
real it can feel. Yeah.
Are there any Easter eggs where you look
at it and go that's unusually accurate
or or you know, that system diagram
actually is like a very
>> Yeah, I I can't I don't think I can even
say them because
there were stories of like early
Dropbox, there were stories of having
ideas ripped off by other companies and
being tricked into having meetings with
folks only to, you know,
it may be even the competitors team
there to to steal the information. A lot
A lot of those stories are real and so
there's people who who watch Silicon
Valley and like, "Oh, wow, that was that
was something I went through." And
probably it was because it was about
that situation.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh [snorts] that's that's such a cool
experience. Uh did did you get paid for
that or was just the Yeah, that's a
complicated question.
>> [laughter]
>> I got paid because I had to get paid
because it was like a Hollywood union
thing. I didn't want to get paid because
it made my visa more complicated. So,
[laughter]
I've got a green card now, I'm all good.
But yeah, but that there was something
where they had to pay me $400. Um
Anyway, I made a grand sum of $400 off
that show.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh looking back on your career, is there
any regret that comes to mind that maybe
other people can learn from?
Uh yeah.
I I mean, ooh.
I think I under invested in my personal
life, to be honest.
I people are probably going to say that
much, you know, because I think you can
be all about like growth. And
you sure I could have grown more. I
could have dropped out of grad school
say 3 years in or 4 years in and
probably would have learned just as
much. I could have taken a job at
Dropbox back, you know, 2 or 3 years
earlier and made a lot more money. Um
everyone has been in the industry long
enough has been offered to co-found
several billion-dollar companies. Like,
everyone has a story about the times
they could have been a billionaire
several times over. Um I don't really
regret those. I think um
Yes, it's it's been a lot of sacrifice
to be
to be blunt. I've been on call my whole
career. You know, I've been I've carried
laptop almost every day.
And there's many
dinners and parties and events I've had
to skip and there's people in my
personal life who have um suffered as a
result and I really appreciate this
people and they they love and care about
me and they know that I just have a
passion for this and so
you know, they they accept me for who I
am. I think it's um
it's it this is like this is, you know,
this is old person talk. But yeah, I
think everyone has to decide like how
much they want to really drive their
career. Cuz there's a trade-off like
absolutely like
I made a tremendous amount of sacrifices
in my career and I really
prioritized
building as probably the num- number one
I mean values first and then building.
But if yeah, if we went back in time,
yeah, I would have had I had a good
life, but I probably would have done
more vacations and you know, I just
I had a bit more of a balanced life. I I
really do think I mean I see that with
all the 996 stuff and and this kind of
performative like,
you know, photos of being in a bar and a
laptop and stuff and I'm like that's not
that's not real. Like that's not I mean
I'm sure I was working more than 996
back then, but like I probably still do
work more than 996, but that's I
but I don't do it like um as a checkbox.
You know, I do it cuz I just really want
to be doing stuff and and so I think
just um
I would have I would caution people
against that hustle culture. I'll I'll
that's not
Firstly, like you you know, you're only
young once. You should you should have
fun. Um you know, I've got quite a few
grays in here, you know.
Um
but um
but also
that's that's that's acting. I mean
focus on solving problems, work hard, be
passionate. Yeah. Yeah, when I studied
your career, I mean
there's there's mentions of you working
at 16 hours a week in various
but um
you know you you like on call you like
fires
you like ownership like all those things
are recipe for working obscene hours.
Yeah, and you know I go home and I'm
tired and I wind down by building stuff
now like I
I'm lucky enough to have a little
workshop at home and so I go home and I
you know make things with my hands.
That's just you know that's just you
become an infra person.
You become an you become an engineer
like in all aspects of your life.
But yeah, I would just I would just say
like
the cool thing is
doing cool stuff that humans use.
The cool thing's not working long hours.
The cool thing's not like showing off
about about that you were running a
coding agent all night. Who cares? The
cool stuff's the cool thing's
enjoying
doing important things.
Do you have a best technical book
recommendation for our people?
Um I mean I have to be honest. I
I haven't read almost any
technical book.
>> [laughter]
>> I mean obviously I was in academia for a
long time. So I read a lot of papers.
Read a lot of papers.
Yeah, learning is awesome. Reading's
great. But balance it, right?
Read something and then go put into
practice and most of my career I have I
mean like sure I did a PhD so I guess
that that is like the academic side. But
after that most of my learning's been by
doing. Cuz there's nothing like being
faced with a real problem in your face
to like to really to really develop as
an engineer.
Yeah, and I think if I answer the
question I'd probably say the same. I
think learning by doing is that's that's
really where where it matters most.
Um and then last question for you is if
you could go back to the beginning of
your career and give yourself some
advice, what would you say?
I'd say
you know what it'll it'll be okay. Like
don't sweat sweat the small stuff as
much. It's hard cuz like my
my whole like engineering brand is about
caring about details and like I I love
like Dieter Rams and like design, you
know, and and and so so being obsessive
is a little bit part of my DNA.
But I think I would go back
and say career's a long I mean there's
just
any story anyone reads about 22-year-old
billionaire blah blah blah just ignore
that story. That's not That's not real.
That's not repeatable. That's not normal
and it's not that healthy and it's not
that good for the people either, right?
You probably won't ideally won't max out
your growth for 20 plus years as an
engineer.
I'm still learning all the time and I've
been an engineer for several decades. Um
so my advice would be don't sweat it.
There's time to grow and I do think that
you know again this is is is a little
bit of a
modern phenomenon but there is a feeling
right now I'm not going to AGI come and
better max out my growth
in the next 3 months. Well, guess what?
You ain't going to do it. It's not going
to happen, right? You can't do it. You
can't max your growth out in the next 3
months. It won't happen. You don't have
to running 17 agents at the same time.
All you got to do is
orient your career around learning every
day and getting better at what you're
doing and trying to solve things in the
most simple ways.
Yeah, I mean on Twitter I I see this
take all the time of this permanent
underclass idea where
you know, if you if you don't make it in
time for AGI then you know, you're going
to be part of this permanent underclass.
Yeah, I mean look, it's a bit
challenging economic times for a lot of
folks and I don't want to be I don't
want to be unsympathetic to people who
are you know, having financial
difficulties.
At the same time it's just not an
instructive attitude. There's not much
you can do with that information other
than feel bad about yourself. And and
and I and I don't and I and someone will
tell someone will argue back, "No, what
you can do is get really good at using
Claude." Well, guess what? It's not very
hard to use Claude. It's not like grab
some Sometimes people tell me like, "Oh
my god, I'm I'm finding it hard to keep
up with all the new models, the new
model drops." I don't even know what the
new models are. Like I I use them, but I
forget the latest model cuz it it
doesn't doesn't matter, right? Like
Like there was this thing called Ralph,
right? I guess it's still Ralph. It's
like a loop thing. I don't really know
what Ralph is, and I haven't heard
anyone mention Ralph in the past few
weeks, but it was the biggest thing in
the in Twitter for like a month. And it
just doesn't this is noise. Somehow
Sometimes I feel like it's like um it's
like tech tabloids. It's like people
think that they're learning by somehow
knowing like listening to what Jensen
said today, or like, "Oh my god, Boris
said that Claude writes itself."
I don't think people you're learn That's
like it's just like reading about
Beyoncé, but you're a nerd and so you're
reading about Jensen, right? But like it
doesn't [laughter] matter. You're not
growing. Like you don't have to know. It
It's okay.
The new coding agent could come out and
you could miss it. And then next year
if if it turns out it's the big one,
you'll just use it. Like it's not hard.
Like I haven't seen any skill so far. I
guess there's some skill, but it's not a
hard skill. If you're good at
engineering, you can figure out how to
use Claude code, right? Or open code.
So, just watch out for tech tabloidism.
It doesn't matter. Just Just be building
stuff. Just Just Just do real crap. Uh I
love I love that mindset and um yeah,
well, that you know, thank you for
>> of it. I'm on Twitter, too. Like I'm you
know, I'm part of the thing. You know,
but like but just ignore me too. Like
>> [laughter]
>> Oh god. All right. Well, thank you so
much for your time, James. I really
appreciate it. This was a lot of fun.
All right. It was great. Thank you.
Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like.
Also, if you have any recommendations
for people you want me to bring on,
please drop a comment. Guests like
Barbara Liskov, Mike Stonebreaker, Mark
Brooker, these were all people that I
brought on because someone left a
comment. On another note, aside from the
podcast, I'm working on building the
ergonomic keyboard that I wish existed.
Here's a glance at the prototype. It's a
split keyboard, so there's two sides. Um
this is in the case. But yeah, we
launched on Kickstarter and we hit our
goal within 8 hours of launching. I
really appreciate it if you were one of
the people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now. And
so, if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.
Thank you again for watching the
podcast, and I'll see you in the next
episode.